so we just described how to read a row
into the sense amplifier and the row
buffer and then get one bit out of that
row so let's suppose that the bits we
had here were one one1 and let's say
this was theam so these bits drained
into the bit line the sense amplifier
amplifies them outputs here one 1 1 1
the row buffer now stores this value and
starts outputting it here let's say that
the column address finally selects this
bit for to be output so we output a z
remember that D reads are destructive
once we do that we no longer have our
bits here so what needs to be done is
after the sense amplifier determines
what the correct values of the bits are
and the cells by now have been exhausted
we reverse the direction and raise each
of the bit lines to its proper value so
now the sense amplifier is driving these
correct values back into the cells and
the cells get their values again so
destructive read from theam means that
really we have to read and then write
each cell so we cannot just wait long
enough to get the value we also have to
wait long enough to put the value back
in the cell this is one of the reasons
why dram is slower than SRAM another
reason of course is that the cell does
not as strongly pull the bit line so the
sense amplifier needs more time to
figure out what it has after after this
read and then write approach the cells
have the correct values for one one1 and
have been refreshed even if they have
reduced to let's say 90% of what they
should have once we read them out and
put it back in we put back in the full
value so now they can again leak for a
while before we need to read and then
write them again so refresh is really
make sure that each of the rows is
readed every once in a while if the time
for the cell to lose the value enough so
that we cannot recover it is some sort
of time T then every row needs to be
read and then written within the time t
a destructive read and then a write will
refesh the row but we cannot rely on the
processor to access every Row in the
memory so that we don't have to do
anything else in fact when you have
caches it often happens that some rows
that are very popular and access by the
processor all the time are actually the
ones that don't get refreshed this way
and the reason is that those become cach
hits and the cach keeps keeping that
data because the processor wants it so
often so we end up actually not
accessing the memory for things that the
processor is accessing the most often so
we cannot even rely on the program to go
through the whole memory so what needs
to happen for refresh is that we have
this refresh row counter it starts at
zero we use it to refresh this row then
it moves to one we then use it to
refresh this row and so on if a row
needs to be refreshed within some
refresh period let's say t and we have n
rows then every T Over N seconds we have
to refresh one row so that by the time
we are done we are ready to refresh
again a row which would only last for a
period of T modern dams have a lot of
rows and the refresh period is well
under a second so we are actually seeing
a lot of refreshes happen every second
this is not something that happens
occasionally this actually significantly
interferes with when we can read and
write our memory cuz while a refresh is
going on we cannot do a useful read
because the row decoder sense amps and
the row buffer are used by the refresh
operation which is reading a row that we
didn't need and writing it back
meanwhile we have to sit and wait with a
real read until that gets done so that
we can move on